Guide to the Dept. of Food and Nutrition records, 1943-1968.
New York State College of Home Economics. Dept. of Food and Nutrition records, 1943-1968.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Dept. of Food and Nutrition records, 1943-1968.
23-14-2485.
New York State College of Home Economics. Department of Food and Nutrition.
3.2 cubic ft.
Records, minutes, correspondence, plans of work, publications, reports, photographs.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library.
Records and photographs of faculty and graduate students in the Dept. of Food and Nutrition of the College of Home Economics.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
In 1969 the Department of Food and Nutrition and the Department of Institution Management merged to become the Department of Human Nutrition and Food.
In 1974 the Board of Trustees voted to abolish the Department of Human Nutrition and Food in the College of Human Ecology and the Graduate School of Nutrition to establish the Division of Nutritional Sciences, an intercollege unit within the Colleges of Agriculture and Life Sciences and Human Ecology.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence, annual reports, minutes of meetings, plans of work, Purnell and Blackhead-Jones Research material, and subject files concerning World War II. Also photographs (identified) of faculty and graduate students in the Department of Food and Nutrition, taken at Mt. Pleasant Lodge, of the Cornell Outing Club, and a notebook kept by Mary W. Meter.
SUBJECTS
Names:
New York State College of Home Economics.; Meter, Mary.; Cornell University--Pictorial Works.; New York State College of Home Economics--Faculty.; New York State College of Home Economics--Students.; New York State College of Home Economics--Curricula.; New York State College of Home Economics.
Subjects:
4-H clubs--New York (State); Nutritional science--Study and teaching.; Women college students.; Children--Nutrition.; Home Economics--Study and teaching.; Infants--Nutrition.; Nutrition.; Victory gardens.; World War, 1939-1945--Food supply--United States.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Committees/Commissions
Boxes 2, 3
Series II. Correspondence
Boxes 2, 3
Series III. Extension Files
Box 1
Series IV. Plans of Work
Box 1
Series V. Publications
Boxes 2, 3
Series VI. Research Files
Boxes 1, 2
Series VII. Reports
Boxes 1, 3
Series VIII. School of Nutrition Files
Box 1
Series IX. Subject Files
Boxes 1-3
Series X. Photographs
Box 4
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Committees/Commissions
  - Emergency Food Commission, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - New York State Emergency Food Commission, 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - New York State Food Commission, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Upstate Food Commission, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Extension Committee on Health and Safety, 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Defense State Nutrition Committee, 1940-1942 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Food and Nutrition Defense Committee, 1941-1943 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Health Committee - War Committee, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Tompkins County Nutrition Committee, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Nutrition - War Committee, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Extension Wartime Council - Defense, 1940-1943 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Home Economics Defense Committee, 1941-1943 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Booklet entitled "Our Job in a World at War," published by the College, Jan. 1942 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - State Nutrition Committee, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Series II. Correspondence
  - Correspondence between Helen Monsch (Head of Dept. of Food and Nutrition) and candidates for regional work in extension, 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Regional Workers - Correspondence, Applications, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Regional Workers - Correspondence, Trip Reports, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Regional Workers - Correspondence, Trip Reports, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Memoranda, Correspondence concerning defense records turned over by Miss Hauck, Fall 1941 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Defense Correspondence, 1940-1942 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Defense Correspondence, 1940-1942 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Series III. Extension Files
  - Extension files
    - Cooperative Extension Narrative Report, Projects V-VII, Home Economics, 1965-1967 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Cooperative Extension Narrative Reports, Projects I-IV, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Cooperative Extension - Annual Reports, Projects I-IV, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Cooperative Extension - Annual Reports, Projects V-VII, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Extension records - Home Demonstration Staff Meeting Minutes, Long Range Planning, 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Extension records - committees, summary of accomplishments, 1961-1963 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Extension records - Memoranda, activity suggestions, committees, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Extension records - Accomplishments, Memoranda, Newsletter, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Extension records - Memoranda, Staff Directory, Minutes, Accomplishments, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Extension records - Base Lines and Projections, Memoranda, Accomplishments, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 4-H Files
    - 4-H correspondence, 1957-1962 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 4-H Club - activity suggestions, minutes of meetings, 1964-1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series IV. Plans of Work
  - Plan of Work, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Plans of Work, 1941-1945 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Plans of Work, 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Plans of Work, 1948-1950 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Plans of Work, 1951-1955 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Plans of Work, 1956-1960 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Plans of Work, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Plans of Work, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Plans of Work, 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Plans of Work, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Series V. Publications
  - War Emergency Leaflets - Defense, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Food Commission list of publications (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Defense -War Emergency Leaflets (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Defense - Publications, Reports, 1940-1942 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Defense - Publications, Reports, 1940-1942 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Defense - Publications, Reports, 1940-1942 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Manual for Writers of Theses, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Senator Desmond article, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Food and Nutrition Publications, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - "Feeding Babies and Their Families" by Helen Monsch and Marguerite Harper, 1943 (Box 4)
    Inscription by Helen Monsch to Jane Barker Pringle
- Series VI. Research Files
  - History of Research - Dept. of Food and Nutrition, 1930's, 1940's (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Purnell and Blackhead - Jones Research, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Purnell and Blackhead - Jones Research, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Purnell and Blackhead - Jones Research, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Purnell and Blackhead - Jones Research, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Purnell and Blackhead - Jones Research, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Purnell and Blackhead - Jones Research, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Purnell and Blackhead - Jones Research, 1940-1942 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Purnell and Blackhead - Jones Research, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Purnell and Blackhead - Jones Research, 1936-1938 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Purnell and Blackhead - Jones Research, 1927-1930 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Purnell and Blackhead - Jones Research, 1930-1932 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Purnell and Blackhead - Jones Research, 1932-1934 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Purnell and Blackhead - Jones Research, 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Purnell and Blackhead - Jones Research, 1935-1936 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Purnell and Blackhead - Jones Research, 1938-1939 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Research in Child Development, Cornell Nursery School, 1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Possible Research Projects, 1930's-1940's (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Dept. Research Policies and Procedures, 1930's-1950's (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Food Dept. - Research, Cornell Research Foundation, Inc., 1932-1942 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Research - Clothing (Cooperative Project with PA State), 1936-1937 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Research - Family Life, 1930-1944 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Research - Memoranda, Projects, Reports of Studies, 1930's-1940's (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Cooperative Research with Physiology Dept., 1936-1943 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Committee on Research in Food Processing, 1942-1945 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Committee on Research in Food Processing, 1942-1945 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Cooperative Research with the Bureau of Human Nutrition and Home Economics, 1944-1946 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Research for Dairyman's League, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - American Dairy Assoc. Research Project, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Research - Approved, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Research - suggested projects, 1942-1946 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Frozen Food Research Committee, 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Housing Research Meeting held in Chicago, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Research for Industry, 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Research - Office of Scientific Research and Development, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Research - Rural Housing, 1942-1946 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Research for War Production Board, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Research - The Aviation Corporation - American Central, 1943-1947 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Series VII. Reports
  - Annual
    - Food and Nutrition Annual Reports - Extension Program, 1932, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Food and Nutrition Annual Reports, 1943, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 4-H Club Annual Reports, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Food and Nutrition Annual Reports, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - 4-H Program Reports, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Food and Nutrition Annual Reports, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - 4-H Club Program, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Food and Nutrition Annual Reports - Extension Program, 1948, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Food and Nutrition Annual Report - Extension Program, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Food and Nutrition Annual Reports - Extension Program, 1952, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Food and Nutrition Annual Reports, 1954, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Food and Nutrition Annual Report, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Food and Nutrition Annual Reports, 1957, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Food and Nutrition Annual Reports, 1959, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Defense
    - Defense Reports, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Quarterly
    - Food and Nutrition Quarterly Reports, 1961-June 1963 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Food and Nutrition Quarterly Reports, October 1963-June 1965 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Food and Nutrition Quarterly Reports, June 1965-March 1966 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Series VIII. School of Nutrition Files
  - School of Nutrition, 1942-1944 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - School of Nutrition, 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - School of Nutrition, 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - School of Nutrition, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Series IX. Subject Files
  - History of Institutional Management (Box 1, Folder 38-39)
  - National Cooperative Project (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Regional Workers, 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Regional Meeting Extension Specialists, 1947-1949 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Summer Canning, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Sugar Substitutes, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Food Preservation, 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Victory Garden Food Preservation School, March 11-13, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Well Baby Clinics, 1935-1938 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Canteen Aids for American Red Cross (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Community Army Suppers and Menus, 1941-1942 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Child Nutrition in Extension, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Civilian Volunteers Participation, 1941-1942 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Mrs. Pennock's Outlines (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Conservation, 1940's (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Notebook kept by Mary Meter Carter, Class of 1945, College of Home Economics, 1943 (Box 4)
  - Course Handouts from Food and Nutrition Course 325, 1968 (Box 4)
- Series X. Photographs
  - Photos of Faculty and Graduate Students in the Dept. of Food and Nutrition, taken at Mt. Pleasant Lodge of the Cornell Outing Club, 1946-1947 (Box 4)